# Faiza Rashid

fayezaarashid@gmail.com | https://azaif7.github.io/ | (647) 467-3193 | Toronto, ON

#### **SUMMARY**

Driven, flexible, dedicated, collaborating and highly skilled Front-End Developer with 5+ years of experience building robust, complex, and accessible user interfaces and applications with strong background in capital markets, web technologies, web development, responsive design, React, Redux, JavaScript, TypeScript, HTML and CSS.

#### **DEVELOPMENT TOOLS**

Software/Languages: Visual Studio Code, Figma, Lucid Charts, Postman, PhpMyAdmin,

Wordpress, SCRUM

Database: MySQL Server

*Operating Systems:* Windows 10, 11, XP/7, MacOS *Other tools:* MS Office, Selenium Web, Google Dev Tools

Web Development: HTML5, CSS3, SCSS Tailwind CSS, Bootstrap 4 & 5, JavaScript, jQuery,

React.js, Redux, Axios, Typescript

**Soft Skills:** Excellent communication skills, Passion for learning and teaching others, thrives in fast paced environment, strong problem-solving skills, reliable, productive and able to write clean and efficient code, debug and troubleshoot any bugs that may arise, experience building progressive and hybrid applications (SASS)

#### PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

# Senior Software Engineer - Front End

Troon Technologies, Pakistan, April 2020–April 2023

- Developed and maintained responsive, high-performance software applications targeting mobile devices and desktop clients in software development
- Utilized modern frontend technologies such as React.js, Typescript, HTML5, CSS, SCSS, Bootstrap, React Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS and JSON to create user-friendly web pages
- Designed and developed Carehubble website for innovative business using React.js, HTML, JS and SCSS with the collaboration of backend team resulting in 5% increase in revenue
- Implemented custom **React hooks**, **Redux**, and **Redux Toolkit** for efficient frontend development, including state management.
- Utilized Formik and React Forms library for building forms with client-side validation using Formik and Yup and server-side rendering using **Axios** library.
- NPM for package installation, react router for navigation through out the project
- Strong understanding of **Virtual DOM** and code refactoring and optimization

- Hands-on understanding of latest paradigms in Frontend Development such as State Management, Web sockets, Web components, Lazy Loading and bundle optimization (webpack)
- Integrated **RESTful APIs** to enhance functionality and user experience
- Worked collaboratively with teams, attending daily SCRUM meetings, sprint planning, and using project management tools like Teamwork and Github for version control while also conducting code reviews, writing tests (Jest and React testing libraries), and deploying bug-free sprints to production.

## Front-End Developer, SyntecX, Islamabad, Pakistan, January 2019-March 2020

- Built web applications using Angular 7+, HTML, CSS, SCSS, Bootstrap, React Bootstrap, Tailwind CSS and JavaScript
- Wrote clean, modular, high-performance, **reusable code**/ UI components/libraries
- Templates and reusable components in Angular and navigation using routes and router module from Angular router module
- Implemented responsive design and cross-browser compatibility using HTML5, CSS3 and Bootstrap 4 and 5
- Components and templates creation using **Angular 7+** and Typescript
- Client side validation using Angular forms and Restful API's integration using Axios library
- Used free tools like google trends to improve **SEO** and **JIRA** for project management
- Slick jquery library to create eye catching carousels
- Utilized **Git** for version control systems and collaborated effectively with team members
- Mentoring junior team members, collaborating with QA team to deliver bug free sprint
- Successfully executed **blockchain** projects involving seamless integration of **wallets**, leading to a significant improvement of **transaction** efficiency by 25% and fostering a 10% growth in user adoption rate.

# Front-End Developer, Ideofuzion, Islamabad. Pakistan, September 2017-December 2018

- Collaborate with web development team to design user interfaces for client websites using HTML5, CSS3, Bootstrap 4 and 5, JavaScript ES6 and Angular
- Assisted in the design, development, and maintenance of **responsive**, high-performance web applications
- Daily ticket resolutions and time logging on JIRA and **Gitlab** for version control
- PSD/Figma/Zeplin prototypes to HTML conversion
- **Slick** library to create high end and eye catching carousels and **Google recaptcha** for verification
- Interface using Angular components and templates

#### **EDUCATION**

- Scholarship from university; 3.63/4.0 GPA
- Certificate of Excellence for the post of Arts and Decoration Head of SoftDesk society

# Virtual University PGD, Computer Science

April, 2021 Islamabad, Pakistan

• 3.89/4.0 GPA

#### **PROJECTS**

## RiskShark (https://riskshark-staging-frontend.troondemo.com)

Riskshark is a product used by analysts which makes it easier for them to analyze the risk status of a company. The purpose of this product is to keep the user updated with all the filings and provide the risk score.

- Developed RiskShark web app using React, Redux, HTML, SCSS and JavaScript.
- Developed reusable UI components using React Hooks and JSX.
- Graphical risk data and stock price displayed using Highcharts.
- Collaborated with devops team to deploy the application on production

## PHC (https://phc-admin-ga.troonlab.io)

This application is a NEMT (Non Emergency Transport) software that streamlines trip booking and makes scheduling, dispatching and billing more efficient.

- Developed PHC (Pioneer Health Care) web app using React, Redux toolkit, HTML, SCSS and JavaScript.
- Developed reusable UI components using React Hooks and JSX.
- Created complex nested tables using React Table library.
- Collaborated with devops team to deploy the application on production

#### REFERENCES

Available upon request